<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning sons and daughters, and prophetesses speaking and prophecying, in the law and the gospel and concerning womens learning in silence and also concerning womens not speaking in the church ...</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40144</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 11327348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11327348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11327348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 : 1460:51, 1641-1700 , 2910:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning sons and daughters, and prophetesses speaking and prophecying, in the law and the gospel and concerning womens learning in silence and also concerning womens not speaking in the church ...</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>P. 11 signed: F.G.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1460:51 imperfect: pages cropped and stained, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Bevan-Naish Collection (1460:51) and Swarthmore College Library (2910:3).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47474:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Concerning Sons and Daughters, and Propheteſſes ſpeaking and Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the Law and in the Goſpel</head>
            <head type="sub">And concerning Womens learning in ſilence,<note place="margin">1 Cor 34.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning womens not ſpeaking in the Church, as the Apoſtle ſaid <hi>I permit not a woman to ſpeak in the Church, and what ſtate they be in, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MIriam</hi> was a Propheteſs the ſiſter of <hi>Aron,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> a Magiſtrate, and <hi>Aron</hi> the Prieſt did not judge this Propheteſs nor other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for they came forth prayſing God together. And <hi>Miriam</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the men, <hi>ſing ye unto the Lord for he hath triumphed gloriouſly,</hi> now are not Chriſtian Prieſts, Rulers and Magiſtrates worſe then <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron</hi> which would ſtop a propheteſs from propheſying? Yea worſe then thoſe that were under the Law, who now profeſs themſelves to be Chriſtians, for the Lord overthrew the horſe and his rider in the ſea, ſaies the Propheteſs; And <hi>Moſes</hi> had been ſinging a little before, and <hi>Miriam</hi> the woman (fell a ſinging) and ſpeaking, the Propheteſs, as you may read <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. and <hi>Moſes</hi> did not reprove her, and the King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> commanded <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the Prieſt and others, <hi>Go a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquire of the Lord for me concerning the words of the Book of the Law,</hi> 2 King. 22.12. and <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the prieſt and others, went unto <hi>Huldah</hi> the propheteſs (a woman teacher) the wife of <hi>Shallum,</hi> and ſhe dwelt in Hieruſalem in the houſe of Doctrine, and they communed with her, and ſhe anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> them, thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael, tell the man that ſent y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me, behold I will bring evil upon this place,</hi> and there you may read in the Chapter what a great ſpeech ſhee made unto them, how ſhe was a teacher both unto the King, and the Prieſt and many others, and how the King did give regard to her words, and ſent to gather together all the Elders of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the Preiſts and Prophets, and declared unto them, of the abomination that had been ſet up which ſhe had witneſſed againſt as before; &amp; ſo here the King &amp; the Prieſts did not diſpiſe this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man teacher; the Prophetſs in the time of the Law, which may condemn Chriſtians, which ſay they are come to the end of the Law, they that are led by the ſpirit are not under the Law but are come to a further ſtate.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. Chap. 1. <hi>He went to the Propheteſs who conceived and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47474:2"/>
bare a Son and then ſaid the Lord call his name</hi> Maher-ſhalal haſh-baz, and here you may ſee here was a Propheteſs not deſpiſed by <hi>Eſai</hi> nor the Lord, <hi>Iudges</hi> 4.4. there <hi>Deborah</hi> a Propheteſs the wife of <hi>Lapidoth</hi> judged <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhe dwelt under a <hi>Palm</hi>-tree, and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came up to her for Judgment and ſhe propheſied (how the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould overcome their Enemies) from the Lord, here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain you may ſee a woman Propheteſs and Teacher, to whom all <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to give Eare who ſaw the overthrowing of their Enemies, then you may read in the 5. of <hi>Iudges,</hi> how <hi>Deborah</hi> praiſed the Lord, and how ſhe called Kings and Princes to hearken, and ſaid ſhe would ſing unto the Lord, and praiſe the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Therefore ye Children of darkneſs, limmit not the holy one, deſpiſe not Prophecying nor the Propheteſſes, who profeſſes your ſelves to be Chriſtians, but ſhews your ſelvs to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant both of Law and Scriptures; and out of the Spirit which gave them forth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>LEt your women learn in ſilence with all ſubjection</hi> 1 Tim. 2. here is a ſilent Learning; a Learning in ſilence; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34.35. <hi>I ſuffer not a woman to teach nor to uſurp Authority over the man, but to be ſilent,</hi> there ſhe is to learn in ſilence and not to uſurpe Authority over the man, but to ask her Husband at home: that which uſurps authority the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> takes hold on, but if you be led of the Spirit then you are not under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. ſo I permit not a woman to ſpeak in the Church as ſaith the Law; ſo <hi>let the woman learn in ſilence with all ſubjection, but I ſuffer not a woman to uſurp Authority over the man but to be in all ſilence;</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> was formed, then <hi>Eve,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> was not deceived but the woman was in the tranſgreſſion, read 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. nevertheleſs ſhe ſhall be ſaved in Child-bearing, if ſhe continue in Faith and Charity and holineſs with ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſo by the leading of the ſpirit ye come to Chriſt, another Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, of whom you are to learn as people were to learn of the Law; and ſuch as are led by the Spirit are the ſons of God, &amp; ſo do prophecy accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Ioel</hi> and <hi>Peter, Ioel</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. &amp; they come from the ſtate that the Law limmits, and theſe did pray and prophecy as inſtance, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.
<pb facs="tcp:47474:2"/>
women praying and prophecying who was a Church, and the Apoſtle ſaith deſpiſe not prophecying.</p>
               <p>Now here is the ſtate of <hi>Eve</hi> and the ſtate of <hi>Ieſabel;</hi> and <hi>Eve's</hi> ſtate is not <hi>Ieſabels,</hi> which are both called women; for <hi>Eve</hi> was firſt decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but daughters prophecying is above <hi>Ieſabels,</hi> and if <hi>Eve</hi> had been in the prophecy ſhe would have foreſeen what ſhe fell into, and prophecy by the Spirit is above the ſtate of the woman, for prophecy does let ſee the deceiver and what he leads into, which though the ſtate of <hi>Eve</hi> muſt be kept under the Law, yet daughters prophecying is in the end of the Law; for <hi>Eve</hi> got over her husband: ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> and doth not ſpeak of quenching Daughters prophecying, not that Chriſt in the Male or in the Female ſhould be ſtopt from ſpeaking which is above <hi>Eve</hi> or <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> read 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. And ſo forbidding a <hi>Ieſabels</hi> ſpeaking, or forbidding a woman in the ſtate of <hi>Eves</hi> ſpeaking is nothing to the purpoſe, for the forbidding of Daughters, or Propheteſſes prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying in the Church, who are led by the Spirit of God or Chriſt in the Females ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>Let your women keep ſilence in the Church, for it is not permited for them to ſpeak, but they are commanded to be under obedience as alſo ſaith the Law, the women which are to be under obedience and to be ſilent and not to ſpeak in the Church as alſo ſaith the Law which doth not permitt; but Chriſt in the Male and in the Female is one which may ſpeak, which makes free from the Law <hi>I will poure out my Spirit upon Sons and Daughters and they ſhall Prophecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as touching womens learning of their Husbands at home, many were Virgins and many Widdows, and many had unbelieving Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; and therefore it muſt either be the Law they were to learn of, or Chriſt; for the Law keeps down that which is to the ſhame, and that which has uſurped Authority, and the Spirit of God leads from that which is a ſhame, and that which has uſurped Authority, and from being deceived. And the Apoſtles which witneſſed Chriſt the end of the Law for righteouſneſs ſake, did allow and own Sons and Daughters prophecying, and women labourers in the Goſpel, which they that are now doctors, Teachers and profeſſors, are againſt; which you never read <hi>Timothy, Titus,</hi> or the Apoſtles did forbid Daughters or women prophecying; and they are ignorant that forbid women or Daughters prophecying; and women labouring in the Goſpel (which is the power of God) and their compairing them to <hi>Ieſabel</hi> ſhews their ignorance <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p>And it is a ſhame for a woman to ſpeak in the Church 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34.
<pb facs="tcp:47474:3"/>
that which the Law forbids, and commands ſilence it is a ſhame to ſuffer them to ſpeak in the Church. What? Came the word of God out from you or came it unto you only? <hi>Paul</hi> according to the meaſure given to him in all his Epiſtles 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. ſpeaking in them of things which ſome are hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, to their own deſtruction; you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beloved ſeeing you know theſe things, bewar leaſt you alſo be led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the error of the wicked and fall from your own ſteadfaſtneſs; 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. but growe in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Peter</hi> which was unlearned in the Letter (yet learned of Chriſt) ſaies ſuch as are unlearned wreſt the Scriptures and the Epiſtles (being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned.) The Scribes, Phariſees, great Rabbies and Doctors, knew not the Scripture being not learned of Chriſt, him who was the life of the Prophets and the end of the Law whom <hi>Peter</hi> was learned in: knew and preached whom they knew not, ſo here the unlearned who was in the life, confounded all the learned out of the life who learned of him by whom the world was made, who comprehended all the world's learning, ſo the unlearned wreſt, they are to learn in ſilence and not to ſpeak as ſaith the Law, but learn of their Husbands at home, Chriſt who makes free from the Law; nevertheleſs ſhe ſhall be ſaved by Child bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſt in the Male, &amp; Chriſt in the Female. Husbands love your wives and be not bitter againſt them: Wives ſubmit your ſelves firſt to your Husbands as unto the Lord; the Husband is the head of the Wife even as Chriſt is the head of the Church, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. &amp; is the ſaviour of the body, therefore as the Church is ſubject to Chriſt ſo let the Wives be ſubject to their own Husbands in every thing, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. Husbands love your Wives even as Chriſt loved the Church and gave himſelf for it, that he might ſanctifie and clenſe it by the waſhing of water by the word: that he might preſent it a glorious Church without ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh, ſo ought men to love their wives as their own bodys, he that loveth his wife loveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for no man ever hateth his own fleſh, but nouriſhed it, and cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it, even as the Lord the Church; for we are Members of his body of his fleſh and of his bones; for this cauſe ſhall a man leave his Father and Mother and be joyned to his wife and they twain ſhall be one fleſh: This is a great miſtery, I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and the Church; he that hath an ear, let him hear this great miſtery; now the unlearned men wreſt it, and the unſtabliſhed who know not this great miſtery; you that are ignorant of the Lords work, and the voice of his Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:47474:3"/>
who are wondring at the Prophecying of the Daughters who make your ſelves ignorant of the Scriptures, and are wondring at the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſes, or his Daughters contrary to <hi>Ioel</hi> the Lords Prophet, which ſpoke from the Lord; and ſaith the Lord to him, <hi>I am the Lord your God and none elſe; and my people ſhall never be aſhamed,</hi> it ſhall come to paſs after thoſe days when Chriſt came, which was the end of the Law, <hi>I will poure forth my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters ſhall Prophecy, and your old men ſhall dream dreames, and young men ſhall ſee viſions, &amp; alſo upon the ſervants &amp; upon the handmaids, in thoſe days will I poure out my ſpirit ſaith the Lord,</hi> Here all may ſee the Spirit of the Lord not limited, but upon the Handmaids and the Servants is the Lords Spirit poured and to be poured; and many thouſands of Servants and Handmaids do witneſs the Spirit of the Lord poured upon them the word of the Lord fulfilled, and upon the Sons and Daughters will the Lord poure out his ſpirit, and they ſhall prophecy: and many Daughters and ſons &amp; young &amp; old men witneſs the ſpirit of the Lord upon them poured out that viſions are ſeen, old men dreame dreames, and young men ſee viſions, and their Sons &amp; their Daughters do prophecy, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.28. and in <hi>Act.</hi> 2. The Apoſtles did there gather together waiting upon the Lord, upon whom the holy Ghoſt fell among them that waited for the Spirit, this prophecy of <hi>Ioel,</hi> they ſaw the fulfilling of, which to the world they were as men drunk, and ſo here the Apoſtles witneſſed the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Prophet, who were witneſſes of Chriſt, whom the Apoſtles did give teſtimony of, and did ſpeak of the Daughters prophecying, and <hi>Phillip</hi> had foure daughters that did prophecy which the Apoſtle did not forbid, and ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. deſpiſe not prophecying &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And when the Apoſtles ſaid the Sons and Daughters ſhould prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they were looked upon by the world, (as men do now) to be drunk.</p>
               <p>And whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid I would all the Lords people were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and there were women that were the Lords people as well as men and women Propheteſſes in his days and in the time of the Law. Therfore you who are called Chriſtians have a minde unlike <hi>Moſes;</hi> and do ſhew that you have not the Spirit of the Lord poured upon you (according to <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.) to prophecy withall who appear to be ſuch as vex &amp; grieve it, and then envy ſuch as prophecy with it and perſecute them. And you do not read that the Jews were offended at old <hi>Hannah</hi> the Propheteſs, who prophecyed in the Temple, which if an old woman ſhould come and prophecy in your Synagogs or Temples, you would cry to the Stocks with her; or to Priſon with her, and haile and perſecute her, though
<pb facs="tcp:47474:4"/>
you be called Chriſtians and ſo do ſhew your ſelves worſe then the Jews. And ſaith the Lord, 1 <hi>Cron.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Touch not mine Anointed and do my Prophets no harme.</hi> So you that perſecute the Daughters on whom the ſpirit of the Lord is poured, and beleeve them not; you are them that deſpiſe the Prophets, and Propheteſſes, and deſpiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying, and ſo have broken the Apoſtles command, who ſaith deſpiſe not prophecying, and ſhews that you are out of the Prophet's doctrin and the Apoſtles doctrin, and againſt the promiſes of God do ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all your might, who ſaith, he would pour forth his Spirit upon all fleſh, and his Daughters ſhould prophecy: And how can you be eſtabliſhed and beleive not the Prophets; for beleiving the Prophets they came to be eſtabliſhed, as you may read 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 20. So how ignorant of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and promiſes of God do the called Teachers of the world make themſelves manifeſt, and how in darkneſs they appear to the children of Light, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.20. So you that deſpiſe prophecying, and caſt the ſons and daughters, ſervants and handmaids into priſons, who witneſs the ſpirit of the Lord God poured forth upon them, you ſhew that you be out of the Apoſtles Doctrine, &amp; to be ſtrangers to the ſpirit, the Scriptures were given forth from, and are ignorant of the Church the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, who ſaith, let the Prophets ſpeak two or three, and let the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judge; if any thing be revealed to one that ſits by, let the firſt hold his peace, for you may all propheſy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted; and the ſpirit of the Prophets is ſubject to the prophets, for God is not the author of confuſion but of peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints, this order was in the Church of the Saints, the Prophets to ſpeak two or three, and the other to judge; <hi>and if any thing be revealed to another that fits by, the firſt held his peace,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30. they might prophecy, all one by one, that all may learn and be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and the ſpirit of the prophets was ſubject to the Prophets, and this was order and not confuſion in all the Churches of the Saints which is diſorder and confuſion in the Churches of the world, who cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a daughter to prophecy, for a daughter might prophecy, a daughter being a propheteſs, where the ſpirit of the Lord is poured forth upon her, for you never read that any of the Prophets or Apoſtles were againſt a daughters prophecying (which had the ſpirit of the Lord poured forth upon them) a daughter might prophecy in the Church, for let your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpeak two or three; <hi>and I will poure out my Spirit upon all fleſh and your daughters ſhall prophecy,</hi> for you that deſpiſe prophecing deſpiſes Gods command and are out of <hi>Moſes</hi> Light and life who ſaid, would all the Lord's people were Prophets, <hi>Num.</hi> 11.26, 27, 28. and daughters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47474:4"/>
are the Lords people; and when they were prophecying in the Campe, there ran a young man and told <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun</hi> the ſervant of <hi>Moſes,</hi> one of his young men anſwered and ſaid, my Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them (like the Prieſt now) <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto him envyeſt thou for my ſake? Would God all the Lord's people were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his Spirit upon them:</hi> Now marke <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwer how backward <hi>Moſes</hi> was from limmitting the Spirit that he would have the Lords ſpirit put upon them all, and ſaid would that the Lords people were all Prophets, ſome of which were women. Now hear you Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, Prieſts and people, which do put into Priſon Sons and Daughters for prophecying; and the Lords people: you ſhew a contrary ſpirit, you ſhew a ſpirit that hath erred from <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpirit, who cannot endure the ſpirit of the Lord ſhould be poured upon them, that they ſhould Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy but would limmit it to Learned men: old Books and Authors. <hi>And</hi> Hannah <hi>the Propheteſs the Daughter of</hi> Phanuel, <hi>which was about fourſcore and foure years of age, came into the Temple, who ſerved God with faſting and praying night and day, ſhe ſpake of Chriſt to all them that looked for Redemption in</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p>Here was a large Teſtimony born of Jeſus by <hi>Hannah</hi> the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36, 37, 38. here you may ſee a daughter which did give Teſtimony of Jeſus, which would be as a wonder in this our age to ſee a woman of four ſcore years of age to ſpeak of Jeſus, to all them that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for redemption in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as ſhe did: put her into Priſon would the wicked ones ſay; into Priſon with her would the Prieſts ſay, &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> the Miniſter of God in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4, <hi>There he intreats his true yoak-fellow to help thoſe women which laboured with him in the Goſpel,</hi> as you may there read the women were joyned with the other fellow labourers, and the Apoſtles whoſe names were written in the Book of life. And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. there you may ſee <hi>Pricilla</hi> and <hi>Aquilla Paul's</hi> helpers in Chriſt Jeſus, who for his life laid down their necks. Here the wife <hi>Pricilla</hi> was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer and was one of them that laid down their necks, and a helper in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24, 25, 26. <hi>She and</hi> Aquilla <hi>took</hi> Appollo <hi>and expounded to him the way of God more perfectly;</hi> one who taught in the Synagogue was inſtructed by her, and him, in the way of God more perfectly, at ſuch your Synagogue Teachers ſcoff, to be inſtructed by a woman: and you that forbid a Womans ſpeaking that hath the ſpirit of the Lord; you forbid Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16, 19. for <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Pricil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> had a Church in their houſe; and the Church in <hi>Pricilla</hi> and <hi>Aquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi>'s houſe was to be Greeted who were inſtructors, and in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Chap. <hi>Act.</hi> 18. he that vvas ſpeaking bouldly in the Synagogue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47474:5"/>
witneſſing <hi>Iohn,</hi> to him <hi>Pricilla</hi> expounded the way of God more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> a Miniſter of the Lord, who witneſſed the daughters prophecying, <hi>I commend unto you</hi> Phebe <hi>our Siſter which is a ſervant of the Church which is at</hi> Cenchrea; <hi>that you receive her in the Lord as becometh Saints, that you aſſiſt her in what buſineſs ſhe hath need of, for ſhe hath been a ſuccorour of many, and of my ſelf alſo.</hi> This was <hi>Phebe</hi> the ſiſter the ſervant of the Church, which was to be received in the Lord, and aſſiſt her in whatſoever buſineſs ſhe hath need. And ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; as touching <hi>Pricilla</hi> and <hi>Aquilla</hi> his fellow labourers in Chriſt Jeſus, who laid down their necks for his life, unto whom he gave thanks and not onely to them but alſo all the Churches of the Gentiles; here you may ſee the account <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Pricilla</hi> were in, who laid down their necks for the Apoſtles how thanks-worthy they were; and <hi>Mary</hi> in ver. 6. was to be greeted, who beſtowed much labour on the Apoſtles you that cannot own the prophecying of the daughters; the women labourers in the Goſpel, you are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. <hi>Which ſerve not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt but your own Bellys, &amp; by the good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> For the obedience of theſe was gon abroad which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, and your diſobedience is gone abroad to the Apoſtle's Doctrine's. Who cannot endure the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of the ſons and daughters, where the ſpirit of the Lord is poured upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Mary Magdalen <hi>ſaw Ieſus after his Reſurection which on the firſt day of the week, came to the Sepulcher, &amp; when ſhe ſaw Ieſus, ſhe knew not that it was him, and ſaid unto him Maſter? Ieſus ſaith unto her touch me not for I am not yet aſcended to my Father, but go unto my bretheren and ſay unto them, I aſcend unto your Father, and my Father; unto your God and my God,</hi> Mary Magdalen <hi>came and told the Diſciples that ſhe had ſeen the Lord, and he had ſpoken theſe things unto her; the ſame day at evening, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt day of the week the Diſciples were aſembled; Ieſus came and ſtood in the midſt and ſaid peace be among you;</hi> Mat 28. Mar. 16. Now here all may ſee that it was <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> that was ſent to declare his reſurrection, and ſhe was to tell the bretheren, the Diſciples whether Chriſt was to go to his Father and our Father, his God and our God, where her Teſtimony was received. Now you that make a ſcoffe and a wonder at a woman's declaring; you may ſee that it was <hi>Mary</hi> that firſt declared Chriſt, after he was riſen, ſo be aſhamed and confounded for ever, and let all your mouths be ſtopt for ever, that deſpiſe the ſpirit of prophecy in the daughters, and do caſt them into Priſon, &amp; do hinder the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47474:5"/>
women labourers in the Goſpel, and ſaith the Apoſtles Chriſt in the Male, and in the Female; and if Chriſt be in the Female as well as in the Male is not he the ſame? and may not the ſpirit of Chriſt ſpeak in the Female as well as in the Male? is he there to be limited? who is it that dare limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the light is the ſame in the Male, and in the Female which cometh from Chriſt, him by whom the world was made, and ſo Chriſt is one in all and not divided; and who is it that dares ſtop Chriſt's mouth, that now is come to Reign in his ſons and daughters, Chriſt in the Male, and Chriſt in the Female; and you that will not have him to Reigne in the Female as well as in the male, you are againſt Scriptures and will not have him to Reigne over you; for in that male where Chriſt doth Reigne, rule and ſpeak 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. he will own Chriſt in the Female there to Reigne, Rule and ſpeak, and come to ſee the Apoſtles doctrine; a Miniſter of Chriſt and of God, and not made by the will of man, who ſaid that Chriſt was in the male and in the Female; Chriſt all in all, and Chriſt in you, <hi>Except you be Reprobates; know you that be Reprobates in whom Chriſt doth not Reigne, nor Rule,</hi> you cannot endure that Chriſt ſhould be in the Female, nor in the Male; but him you will hayle into Priſon, and yet profeſs the words as the Phariſees did to whom Chriſt ſaid <hi>I was ſick and in Priſon, and you viſited me not, and I was naked and hungry and ye cloathed me not nor fed me,</hi> now them which had Scripture; and would not have Chriſt to Reigne, <hi>ſaid when ſaw we thee in Priſon, or naked, and hungry and we Cloathed thee not? or viſited thee not, in as much as you did it not to the leaſt of theſe, you did it not unto me ſaid Chriſt,</hi> So if they who viſited him not in Priſon, who had the Scriptures to talk on of Chriſt that was to come; as you have of one which is come; and would not have him Reigne, as you will not now, ſuch were to go into puniſhment, prepared for the Devil and his Angles; if ſuch puniſhment come upon them that viſited him not, when he was caſt into Priſon; what will come upon you that do him caſt into Priſon? but Chriſt is come to Reigne; him by whom the world was made, who now Reignes in his ſons and daughters; and in the male and in the female.</p>
               <p>That the glory is ſeen; that the Son had with the father before the world began, which Glory thoſe males and females that receive Chriſt, do ſee that the ſpirits of the Prophets is ſubject to the Prophets, whether it be ſon or daughter, that prophecies; and the Prophets may ſpeak one by one in the true Church, and a daughter is a Propheteſs and may prophecy as well as a ſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31, 32, 33. <hi>Now every one having a light from Chriſt Ieſus the ſon of God; him by whom
<pb facs="tcp:47474:6"/>
the world was made, being turned to the light, turned to Chriſt,</hi> I ſay him by whom the world was made, and ſee him the Prophet whom God had raiſed up, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoke of who is the end of the Prophets, and with the light ſee Chriſt the Gift of God, the promiſe of the father, and receive him you will ſee with the light, ſuch as act contrary to the light which they are lighted withal, what due and portion is to them who contrary to the light do act, which comes from Jeſus Chriſt, and with the light you will ſee the promiſe to them of life, that walk in the light that comes from Jeſus, and every one receiving the light that comes from Chriſt, you ſhall receive the ſpirit of prophecy, whether you be male or female, and the ſpirit of prophecy is the Teſtimony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus, if male or female have received the Teſtimony of Jeſus, they have received the ſpirit of prophecy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</p>
               <p>And many women are helping labourers in the Goſpel now, which lay down their necks, whoſe names are written in the book of life; in this time the Goſpel is preached again according to <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. but in the time of the beaſt, falſe Church and Antichriſt they have bin forbidden by them, &amp; <hi>Phebe</hi> was a Miniſter or ſervant or Paſtor (as ſome Tranſlations hath it) of the Church at <hi>Cencrea.</hi> Here <hi>Paul</hi> who forbad womens ſpeaking in the Church, did encourage theſe labouring women in the Goſpel: Though the Apoſtle who ſee ſuch women as were buiſy bodys, tatlers, and run up and down, he rebukes them and brings them under the Law, which were gon into the deceived ſtate as <hi>Eve</hi> was; and he ſaid it was a ſhame for ſuch women to ſpeak in the Church, for ſuch were in that nature that would uſurpe authority over the man; and ſuch were to be limmitted according to the Law, for they ran into that which brought the ſhame which the Apoſtle Iudged; but he ſets forth the comlineſs in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. how women ought to pray &amp; prophecy, and recorded it as a commendation, the womens labouring in the Goſpel and <hi>Phillips</hi> daughters prophecying, and <hi>Pricilla</hi> and <hi>Phebe,</hi> and did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſuch; ſo he made diſtinction here, and preached Chriſt in the male and female, who is above <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> who is above <hi>Eve,</hi> and the ſtate of a womans not ſpeaking; and he in the females may ſpeak, or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſes of him by the ſpirit of God, and this the Apoſtle holds forth, who was not made a Miniſter by the will of man; which they that are made by the will of man denies. And the Apoſtles did not judge <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> for declaring to them the Reſurrection of Jeſus, nor tell her they did not ſuffer a woman to ſpeak, but we ſay all the women in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome that know the death of Jeſus; and his Reſurrection, and are dead with him and riſen with him (that know his Reſurrection) may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47474:6"/>
freely declare it, and they that are in the ſpirit of Chriſt as the Apoſtles were, would not Judge them.</p>
               <p>And we ſay they that are like <hi>Hannah</hi> the propheteſs that ſee Chriſt Jeſus the Saviour and doth confeſs him to all that look for Redemption in Chriſtendom, both of the Chriſtians and Jews, we are not againſt ſuch Propheteſſes though many of the peviſh Prieſts are.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Simeon</hi> the juſt man did not finde fault with <hi>Hannah</hi> for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, to all them that looked for Redemption in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> nor <hi>Zachary</hi> the Prieſt, neither did they tell her that a woman muſt not ſpeak, and <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelation, ſaid the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prophecy by which they overcame, now if all women have the Teſtimony of Jeſus, have not they then the ſpirit of prophecy? and if all be led by the ſpirit of God are they not then from under the Law? and then may they not prophecy? for there is none that will finde fault with the daughters prophecying; &amp; women labourers in the Goſpel, but ſuch as do not live in the Teſtimony of Jeſus, which is the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy; and ſuch do not underſtand the condition that theſe women were in, that <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſuffer nor permit to ſpeak in the Church, but to be in ſilence as alſo ſaith the Law, and are not led by the ſpirit of God, nor do live in it, nor in the Teſtimony of Jeſus, but are in the diſobedience as <hi>Eve</hi> was, and ſo goes into tatlings and goes out of truth as <hi>Ieſabel</hi> did; for in the diſobedience comes the ſhame and uſurping, upon which goes the Law, and the not permitting to ſpeak, for the ſpeaking as moved of the Lord, is in the obedience to the power &amp; ſpirit which does not bring to uſurpe over the man, as the diſobedience doth, which the man Chriſt comes over, which he in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le and in the female may ſpeak, which is one, which ends the Law, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rowes down that which uſurped Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that brought and brings the ſhame, and there the ſeed of God is over all ſet, and the top ſtone laid; and ſo farwell Sons and Daughters.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. G.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb facs="tcp:47474:7"/>
               <p>For Sons and daughters fellowſhip is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of prophecy the Teſtimony of Jeſus. And alſo <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of young men and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> praiſing the Lord <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and do not your women ſpeak in the Church when they ſing in your Steeple houſes called Churches? And muſt any ſing without the ſpirit, and if they ſing with the ſpirit may they not prophecy and pray with the ſame ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where does the Apoſtles limmit them to one ſervice, and not to the other.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London <hi>Printed for</hi> M. W.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
